So, I'm gonna give a series of 4 lectures
on Proof Theory and its foundations
And ... already set me up to some extent in terms of the first lecture.
you can think of this as being titled Judgements and propositions
so I will draw the distinction, and talk about
how we actually define a logic
what is a logic, how do we define it
how do we work with it
and things like that
and if you think about the trinity picture
that Bob drew
so, we had a Proof Theory over here
and Logic, and here we have Type Theory
over here, and we had Category Theory over here
we can also think of this slightly different point of view
you can think of this as being mostly the domain of Philosophy
if you will.
And of course we know how these things are connected.
and this is Computer Science
and this is Maths
and one of the reasons why we're doing this kind of thing
together is to show that they're all aspects of
the same thing that we're trying to do.
Today in the first lecture I'll stay mostly in this
in this realm here, Philosophy, Logic and Proof Theory
even though I'll make some brief connections to the other topics.
and then, in the second lecture
I'll taks about Proofs as programs
I reserve the right to adjust this lecture, as I see what Bob's actually doing
I'm gonna try to move a bit into this direction
ok, so away from this, into this direction
in the third one I'll talk about Proof search
this is a very important topic
perhaps not so much because, I mean there is a connection, of course
in this picture
on this side, we can ??? Sequent Calculus
but also, if you use a sistem like Coq
then you're doing Theorem Proving
and when you're doing Theorem Proving you need to understand
how you search for proofs
and so it's very important to talk about the
basic principles of Proof search you can use this kind of things effectively
so that's the third lecture
and I'm kind of still edging my bets
on the fourth lecture, to see
exactly what I'm gonna do. What I did last year was
called focusing, and I might do that again
or I might brach out in some different direction, talk about
some other topic, like Monads
and things like that
let's come to the first topic
Judgements and propositions
what I've already ??? the basic idea
that we have when we make a judgement, something like "a is true"
and this thing here is a proposition
and the thing taken as a whole, that's what we call a Judgement
And Martin Lof would say that a judgement is an object of knowledge
it is something that we actually know
where a proposition is something in particular
about which we make ??? different judgements
and so we can think of other judgements to make about propositions, besides the fact that they're true
so another judgement I want to make, for example is to say
it is false
that a typical judgement that we often make
about a proposition
another judgement you this morning
which is
? is a proof of a or
equivalent to say that M is
a program which has type A
so we know that, by the connection between
two pause on this triangle there
that these are really the same thing
it's another judgement